Guide to the William Hurlin Papers
Yale University Divinity School Library
William Hurlin Papers
1848-1909
RG 289
Yale University Divinity School Library
3
(7 boxes)
This collection documents the professional work of William Hurlin, who served as pastor for various Baptist churches in New England and was also involved in Baptist work on the state level, particularly in New Hampshire.
Hurlin, William, 1814-1910
Biographical / Historical
William Hurlin was born July 31, 1814, in London, England. He joined a Wesleyan Methodist church in 1832, and became active in tract distribution. He preached his first sermon in 1835 in Illford, a London suburb at that time. In 1840 he became a London City Missionary in the Kingsland district, and continued service with the organization until 1849, when he moved to the United States. He had been baptized and united with a Baptist church in 1842.
In the States he was ordained pastor of a Free Baptist church in North Danville, Vermont, in 1850. He held Free Baptist pastorates in Alton, New Hampshire, Acton, Maine, and Amesbury, Massachusetts. In 1855 he affiliated with the American Baptist denomination and held the following pastorates: Acton, Maine (1856-1858), East Sumner, Maine (1858-1861), Damariscotta Mills, Maine (1861-1864), China, Maine (1864-1866), Antrim, New Hampshire (1866-1873), Plaistow, New Hampshire (1875-1877), and Goshen, New Hampshire (1877-1878).
He was active in Baptist work on the state level. He was a member of the Board of Trustees of New Hampshire Baptist Convention from 1866 until his death in 1910 and was secretary of the Convention 1878-1899. He was also treasurer and statistical secretary of the New Hampshire Baptist Ministers' Conference. Hurlin wrote a history of every New Hampshire Baptist church and prepared a brief biography of most ministers ever associated with the Convention. In addition he was a frequent contributor of articles to denominational journals.
He lived in Antrim the last 32 years of his life, and died there June 28, 1910.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Transferred from Andover Newton Theological School Collection, 2017
Scope and Contents
The William Hurlin Papers, 1848-1909, document the professional work of Hurlin. The collection is arranged according to the following categories: sermons, lectures, addresses, list of readings, unpublished literary manuscripts, scrapbooks of publications, and photographs.
Arrangement
Series I. Sermons
Series II. Lectures
Series III. Addresses
Series IV. List of Readings
Series V. Unpublished Literary Manuscripts
Series VI. Scrapbooks of Publications
Series VII. Photographs
Baptists -- New England
- Sermons, Series I
  Scope and Contents
  Sermons are arranged in numerical order assigned by WH. When originally written, the numerical order was also chronological. However, the sermons in their present form are revisions of the earlier sermons. Therefore, the numerical order is no longer chronological. See the numerical list of sermons in the first folder for the original dates of the sermons.
  - List of sermons preached (numerical listing) (Box 1)
  - List of sermons preached, 1840-1854, 1891 (Box 1)
  - List of funeral sermons, 1850-1866, 1873-1876
  - Sermon numbers 102-106, 108-109, 111, 113-118, 120-124, 126-132, 134-137, 139, 141-157, 159-170, 172-175, 178-179, 182-190, 192-197, 200, 202-203, 205-207, 209-222, 224-225, 227-228, 230-236, 238-241, 243-260, 262-340, 342-347, 351-369, 370-383, 385-396, 398, 400-412, 414-432, 435-444, 446-485, 487, 489-492, 494-505, 508-511, 514-519, 522-524, 526-527, 529-537, 1850–1906 (Box 1)
  - Sermon numbers 538-548, 550-553, 556-559, 561-569, 571-574, 576-590, 592-594, 596-643, 646-650, 661-683, 685-687, 689-696, 698, 700-702, 704, 706-720, 723, 725, 801-822, 870, 917, 920, 927, 946, 1848-1906, no date; 2 (Box 2)
- Lectures, Series II
  - England ( 2 drafts), No date (Box 2)
  - London (3 drafts), No date (Box 2)
  - Pilgrim's Progress (10 lectures), No date (Box 2)
- Addresses, Series III
  - Funeral of John S. Wilson, No date (Box 2)
  - Temperance, No date (Box 2)
  - 4 untitled addresses, No date (Box 2)
  - Address at Farewell Tea Meeting Kingsland, 1849 May 21 (Box 2)
  - Speech for Wheelock -- M. Home, 1849 October 27 (Box 2)
  - Appeal on Sabbath, 1849 October 28 (Box 2)
  - 3 untitled addresses, 1857, 1858, 1877 (Box 2)
  - Missionary Life in Persia. and the Koordish Mountains, 1869 December 21 (Box 2)
  - Address. at Bible Society at Lyndeboro, 1889 October (Box 2)
- Notes on Reading, Series IV
  - List of articles and books in alphabetical order, 2 volumes, No date (Box 2)
- Unpublished Manuscripts, Series V
  - Emmanuel, God with us (3 drafts), No date (Box 3)
  - General Catalogue of Pastors of Baptist Churches in New Hampshire from 1832 to 1892, 1907 (Box 3)
  - Brief Histories of the Baptist Churches in New Hampshire, 1904 (Box 4)
  - Miscellaneous, No date (Box 4)
- Scrapbooks, Series VI
  Scrapbooks contain clippings of articles by Hurlin
  - Articles in The Baptist, 1875–1894 (Box 4)
  - Articles in Boston Journal and Boston Transcript, 1864–1899 (Box 4)
  - Articles in The Christian Era, 1868–1875 (Box 4)
  - Articles in The Morning Star, 1849–1850 (Box 4)
  - Articles in The Morning Star, 1869–1880 (Box 5)
  - Articles in The Morning Star, 1881–1895 (Box 5)
  - Articles in National Baptist, 1865–1876 (Box 5)
  - Articles in Watchman and Reflector, 1854–1856 (Box 5)
  - Articles in Watchman, Boston Journal, 1876–1909 (Box 5)
  - Articles in Zion's Advocate, 1856–1867 (Box 5)
  - Articles in Zion's Advocate, 1858 (Box 5)
  - Articles in Zion's Advocate, 1868–1909 (Box 6, 7)
  - Articles in miscellaneous newspapers, 1860–1875 (Box 7)
- Photographs, Series VII
  - Photographs of individuals, No date (Box 7)
    Individuals include: Willard Ashmore, Swatow, China; John Clifford; John E. Clough, Ongole, India; William Dean, Siam; Mrs. William Dean, Siam; Millard P. Johnson; Oliver Wendell Holmes; Alvah Hovey; Emory W. Hunt; Edward Judson; John F. McElwain; C.A. Nichols and son Bertie - Bassein, Burma; John R. Mott; Harrington Putnam; Walter Rauschenbusch; Augustus H. Strong (2); Willis F. Thomas [and family], Insein, Burma
  - Photograph of the Home for Children of Missionaries, Newton Centre, MA, No date (Box 7)
  - Pictures of buildings, mostly clippings from magazines, No date (Box 7)
  - Pictures of individuals, mostly clippings from magazines, No date (Box 7)